Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Don Johnston Papers, 1964-1996 and undated RL.00717
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Don Johnston papers
1964-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00717
17.5 Linear Feet
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Don Johnston held many positions at JWT, beginning his career as a trainee in the Detroit mailroom and retiring as CEO and President. The Don Johnston Papers span the years 1964-1996 and document his career in various positions with JWT. The collection includes international and domestic inter-office correspondence, personal and administrative files, management manuals, presentations, speeches, budgets, billings and profit reports, and video-cassettes that relate to planning for JWT projects, committee meetings, marketing research, contracts with clients, management directives, and JWT's corporate mission and philosophy. The papers also touch on Joseph O'Donnell's attempted hostile takeover of the JWT Group, and the purchase of JWT by the WPP Group. Clients represented include: Ford Motor Company, Unilever, Chevron, General Foods, and Uniroyal Tire. Offices represented include: Buenos Aires, Toronto, Chicago, Santiago, Detroit, Paris, Frankfurt, Bombay (Mumbai), London, Tokyo, New York, and Johannesburg.
12000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Don Johnston Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as transfers in 1995 and 2003.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1927 Born George Donald Johnston, Elmira, NY
1950 B.S., Summa Cum Laude, in Journalism and Economics, Michigan State University
1951 Began career with JWT as a trainee in Detroit Office mail room
1952 M.A with Honors in International Economics, School of Advanced International Studies, Johns Hopkins University. Johnston attended on a JWT scholarship.
1952 Assistant International Account Representative, JWT New York
1953 Representative, JWT Colombia
1956 Account Representative and Account Supervisor, JWT New York
1961 Managing Director, JWT Amsterdam
1964 Managing Director, JWT Tokyo
1966 Vice President-Europe, JWT Frankfurt
1967 Vice President-Europe, JWT London
1971 Senior Vice President, JWT Latin America
1972 Member of Board of Directors and Executive Committee Executive Vice President-International JWT New York
1974 President and CEO of JWT Company
1978 Chairman of JWT
1980 Chairman of newly formed JWT Group Inc. Chairman of American Association of Advertising Agencies Won International Advertising Association Annual Award.
1986 Established Sarita and Don Johnston Professorship in Latin American Studies at Johns Hopkins University
1987 Retired from JWT
Upon retirement from the JWT, Johnston was named Chairman of the International Executive Service Corps. Johnston is currently a Trustee Emeritus of Johns Hopkins University.
Collection Overview
The Don Johnston Papers span the years 1964-1996 and document his career in various positions with JWT. The collection includes international and domestic inter-office correspondence, personal and administrative files, management manuals, presentations, speeches, budgets, billings and profit reports, and video-cassettes materials that relate to planning for JWT projects, committee meetings, marketing research, contracts with clients, management directives, and JWT's corporate mission and philosophy. The papers also touch on Joseph O'Donnell's attempted hostile takeover of the JWT Group, and the purchase of JWT by the WPP Group. Clients represented include: Ford Motor Company, Unilever, Chevron, General Foods, and Uniroyal Tire. Offices represented include: Buenos Aires, Toronto, Chicago, Santiago (Chile), Detroit, Paris, Frankfurt, Bombay (Mumbai), London, Tokyo, New York, and Johannesburg (South Africa).
The collection is organized into four series: Memoranda, Administrative Files, Personal Files, and Audiovisual Materials.
The Memoranda Series includes business correspondence to and from Johnston during his career with JWT and mainly pertains to the day to day operations throughout the worldwide operations of JWT as a transnational entity.
The Administrative Files Series includes reports, plans, inter-office correspondence, general administrative files, as well as information on fund-raising for the JWT archives at Duke University.
The Personal Files Series includes newspaper and periodical clippings, as well as personal correspondence.
The Audiovisual Materials Series consists of promotional works and interviews by Johnston during his tenure with JWT.
Related materials within the JWT Archives may be found in these collections: the Burt Manning Papers, the Thomas Sutton Papers, the Rena Bartos Papers, the Harry Clark Papers, the Joseph O'Donnell Papers, the Greg Bathon Papers and the Denis Lanigan Papers.
Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising agencies -- Europe; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- Latin America; Photographs; Advertising; Videocassettes; Speeches; J. Walter Thompson Company. Mumbai Office; Chevron Corporation; Grisman, Arnold; General Foods Corporation; WPP Group plc; Ford Motor Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Johannesburg Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Buenos Aires Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Santiago (Chile) Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Tokyo Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Paris Office; J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; J. Walter Thompson Company. Toronto Office; Unilever (Firm); Uniroyal, Inc.; Johnston, Don, 1927-; O'Donnell, Joseph W.
- Memoranda Series, 1974-1984, 17 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of memoranda to and from Johnston from 1969-1984. Includes inter-office memoranda as well as inter-business correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1974, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1975, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1975 Oct.-1976 Sept., 6 folders (Box 3)
  - 1976 Oct.-1977 Dec., 5 folders (Box 4)
  - 1978, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1979 June-Sept., 7 folders (Box 6)
  - 1979 Oct.-1980 Jan., 7 folders (Box 7)
  - 1979 Jan.-May, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - 1980 Feb.-Sept., 6 folders (Box 9)
  - 1980 Oct.-1981 Mar., 6 folders (Box 10)
  - 1981 Mar.-June, 7 folders (Box 11)
  - 1981 July-Dec., 7 folders (Box 12)
  - 1982 Jan.-May, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - 1982 June-1983 Jan., 5 folders (Box 14)
  - 1983 Feb.-Sept., 5 folders (Box 15)
  - 1983 Oct.-1984 June, 6 folders (Box 16)
  - 1984 July-Dec., 4 folders (Box 17)
- General Administrative Files Series, 1964-1996 and undated, 2 boxes
  Includes general files, client files, correspondence between Johnston and various JWT offices, historical material on JWT, reports and speeches. The series is organized into five subseries--Administrative Files, Client Files, Historical, Inter-Office Correspondence, and Projects, Reports and Speeches--and alphabetically therein.
  - Administrative Files Subseries, 1964-1986
    - AAA (Agency Art Association), 1974 (Box 18)
    - Account teams, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Advertising agency correspondence, 1980 (Box 18)
    - Annual reports, 1973-1978, 6 folders (Box 18)
    - Board of Directors, 1975-1976 (Box 18)
    - Client/Agency review, undated (Box 18)
    - Client retention reports, 1978-1981 (Box 18)
    - Corporate advertising, 1975-1978 (Box 18)
    - Diners/Fugazy, 1974-1975 (Box 18)
    - Executive committee, 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Flagship, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Formal reporting, 1974 (Box 18)
    - IMG (International Management Group), 1973-1979, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - JWT Group, 1986 (Box 19)
    - JWT subsidiaries
      - AMRB (Axiom Market Research Bureau), 1976 (Box 19)
      - Deltakos, 1974-1975, 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Diogenes, 1975 (Box 19)
      - Interlease, 1975-1976 (Box 19)
      - Lintas, 1972 (Box 19)
      - Lord, Geller, Federico, 1976 (Box 19)
      - Synapse, 1974 (Box 19)
      - Univas, 1979 (Box 19)
    - London Office, 1972 and undated (Box 19)
      [Includes a poster of London Board of Directors; materials pertaining to a Latin American Managers' meeting in London; a visitor's guide to Soho.]
    - Managers manual, undated, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Media, 1974-1977 (Box 19)
    - Meek, Sam, undated (Box 19)
      Meek (1895-1981) was Vice President in Charge of International Operations until his retirement in 1964.
    - Mission and philosophy, 1964-1981 (Box 19)
    - Multinational account management, 1978-1979 (Box 19)
    - Recruiting, 1979-1980 and 1984 (Box 19)
    - Standard operating procedure, 1980 (Box 20)
    - Technology, 1974 and undated (Box 20)
    - Troutbeck meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 20)
      Contains memoranda about the meetings in 1980 and 1981 at the Troutbeck Inn in Amenia, N.Y. to discuss the creation and implementation of the JWT Group.
  - Client Files Subseries, 1971-1988 and undated
    - 20th Century Fox, 1981-1983 (Box 20)
    - Amtorg, 1974 (Box 20)
    - Braun, 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Burger King, 1976 and 1988, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Chevron, 1977 (Box 20)
    - Congoleum, 1979 (Box 20)
    - Continental Car, 1974 (Box 20)
    - DeBeers, 1972-1983 (Box 20)
    - Emery, 1981 (Box 20)
    - Florida Grapefruit Association, 1982 (Box 20)
    - Ford Motor Company
      - General, 1973-1974 (Box 20)
      - Audit, 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Europe, 1982-1982, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - Germany, 1985-1986 (Box 20)
      - International, 1985 (Box 20)
      - Letter of Terms, 1973 (Box 20)
      - Permanent File, undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - General Foods, 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Gilette, 1975 (Box 21)
    - Goodyear, 1981 (Box 21)
    - Heineken/Guinness, 1973 (Box 21)
    - Institute of Life Insurance, 1974-1975 (Box 21)
    - Joh. Jacobs and Co., 1974 (Box 21)
    - Kellogg's, 1974-1975 (Box 21)
    - Kodak, 1983 (Box 21)
    - Kraft, 1974 (Box 21)
    - Labatt's, 1974 (Box 21)
    - Lever Brothers, 1972 (Box 21)
    - Mentholatum, 1974 (Box 21)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., 1975 (Box 21)
    - Nestlé, 1982 (Box 22)
    - Orkin, 1976 (Box 22)
    - Pearle, 1981 (Box 22)
    - Pillsbury, 1983 (Box 22)
    - R.J. Reynolds, 1980 (Box 22)
    - Ryder, 1983 (Box 22)
    - Scott, 1979 (Box 22)
    - S.C. Johnson, 1970s and undated (Box 22)
    - Schlitz, 1978 (Box 22)
    - TWA, undated (Box 22)
    - Unilever, 1971-1973
      - 1971-1973, 12 folders (Box 22)
      - 1974, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Uniroyal, 1973, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - United States Marine Corps, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Vereinigte Papierwerke, 1973 (Box 23)
    - Warner-Lambert, 1974 (Box 23)
  - Inter-Office Communication Subseries, 1969-1982
    - Argentina, 1978 (Box 23)
    - Canada, 1977-1978, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Chicago, 1978 (Box 23)
    - Chile, 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Detroit, 1977-1978 (Box 24)
    - Europe, 1976 and 1978-1982, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Far East, 1978-1981, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - France, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Frankfurt, 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - India, 1970s, 5 folders (Box 25)
    - International:
      - General, 1970s, 4 folders (Box 25)
      - Europe, 1970s, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Memoranda, 1970s, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Seminars, 1969-1973 (Box 26)
    - Japan, 1973-1974 (Box 26)
    - Latin America, 1976-1980, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - London, 1978-1981 (Box 26)
    - Madrid, 1979-1980 (Box 26)
    - South East Asia, 1976 (Box 26)
    - South Africa, 1979 (Box 26)
    - Treasure, John, 1973-1978 (Box 26)
      Treasure was Chairman of JWT London from 1967-1974.
    - U.S. Inter-office, 1975 (Box 26)
  - Projects, Reports, and Speeches Subseries, 1973-1996 and undated
    - JWT Reports and Projects
      - Advertising and Black America, 1977 and undated (Box 26)
      - Advertising and Spanish speaking America, undated (Box 26)
      - Chile (Box 27)
        - Informe de la visite a Chile, 1973-1974 (Box 27)
          Entirely in Spanish.
        - Report on Chile, 1973-1974 (Box 27)
      - Consumers in Crisis, 1974 (Box 27)
      - Desensitization of America to Violence, 1976, 3 folders (Box 27)
      - Dialog, 1974 (Box 27)
      - Diversification and Business project, 1974 (Box 27)
      - Duke University, JWT archives, 1990 (Box 27)
        Contains fund-raising letters written by Johnston and other former and current JWT executives on behalf of the Hartman Center at Duke University.
      - Future Environment for Advertising, 1977 (Box 27)
      - JWT Consumer Advertising, 1974 (Box 27)
      - Managing a JWT Office for Profit and Performance, 1978, 3 folders
        Presentations at the Fifth JWT World Management Meeting in 1978. Presenters included Denis Lanigan, Burt Manning, and Marie Luisi.
        - Clients, Client Relations, and Client Service: Their Effect on the Agency Performance and Profit and How to Manage Them (Box 27)
        - Growth and Return on JWT Investment (Box 27)
        - Is There a Crisis in Branding in the U.S.? (Box 27)
        - JWT: Reputation and Reality (Box 27)
        - People--A New York Office Perspective (Box 27)
        - Product and Profit: You Can't Have One Without the Other (Box 27)
        - Profit (Box 27)
        - Reshaping JWT for Future Needs and Opportunities (Box 27)
        - The New Medium: Television in the 1980's (Box 27)
        - Yes, But What Responses? (Box 27)
      - Managing the Agency, circa 1978 (Box 27)
      - Media Buying: Recommendations for a JWT Test Market in Europe, 1972 (Box 27)
      - Rena Bartos research surveys, 1973-1974 (Box 27)
      - Research and Media, 1977-1981, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - [Spain--Las ramblas de Barcelona moved to Oversize Folder 1.] (Box 27)
      - T-Plan, 1972-1974, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - Women--Lorrell Burke study, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Speeches
      - Don Johnston speeches, 1977-1996 and undated, 5 folders (Box 28)
      - JWT Executive Speeches, 1974-1983 (Box 28)
        Includes speeches by Denis Lanigan, John Treasure and Wayne Fickinger.
- Personal Files Series, 1973-1987 and undated
  Contains personal correspondence that related mainly to the hostile takeover attempt of JWT by Joseph O'Donnell, the WPP takeover of JWT, and Johnston's retirement from JWT. Organized into two subseries--JWT History and Personal Correspondence--and alphabetically therein.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Original correspondence from notable individuals is closed to researchers. Photocopies can be found in the respective folders.
  - Historical Subseries, 1973-1987 and undated
    - Articles and interviews, 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Going private, 1974 (Box 28)
    - JWT history, 1983 (Box 28)
    - Replacing Tom Sutton, 1970s (Box 28)
    - Succession planning, 1984-1985 (Box 29)
    - WPP takeover
      - JWT treachery, 1986-1987 (Box 29)
      - Photos with Joe O'Donnell, undated (Box 29)
      - WPP Takeover, 1987 (Box 29)
  - Personal Correspondence Subseries (RESTRICTED), 1976-1987
    - Autographed letters, 1978-1985 (Box 29)
      [Contains photocopies of letters written by Jacqueline Onassis, Henry Kissinger, and Jimmy Carter to Johnston. Originals are closed to patron use.]
    - Correspondence from outside directors, 1976-1980, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Correspondence from retired directors, 1976-1982, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Johnston's retirement from JWT
      - Client responses to retirement, 1987 (Box 29)
      - JWT responses to retirement, 1987 (Box 29)
      - Personal responses to retirement, 1987 (Box 29)
      - Post takeover letters, 1987 (Box 29)
    - Other letters, 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Restricted material, 1978-1985
    - Autographed letters, 1978-1985 (Box 30)
      Contains letters written by Jacqueline Onassis, Henry Kissinger, and Jimmy Carter to Johnston.
      Restriction Note: Original letters are closed to patrons. Use copies can be found in box 29.
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1987 and undated, 3 boxes
  Consists of video tapes of presentations given by Johnston. Originals and Reference Master copies are closed to patron use.
  - Originals (CLOSED)
    - OR1. CEO Closeup: Don Johnston, undated. VHS. (Box 30)
    - OR2. Don Johnston: The Best Thompson Yet, 1987. VHS. (Box 30)
    - OR3. The Thompson Way, undated. VHS. (Box 30)
  - Reference Master copies (not for reference use)
    - Video materials (Box 31)
      Format: BetacamSP. Created: 2006.
      - MC1-MC3 (Box 31)
  - Use copies
    - Video materials (Box 32)
      Format: DVD. Created: 2006.
      - UC1-UC3 (Box 32)
- Oversize Materials, 1 folders
  - JWT Spain--Las ramblas de Barcelona, 1974 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    [Photographs and art with essay on Barcelona's main street. Text in Spanish.]
  - Press articles and mentions, 1969-1984 (Oversize-folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Advertising Age "TWST names Johnston best chief executive advertising industry"; Sunday Times "Operation Checkmate" on vetting prospective executive's spouses